Finding Aid for Brewer General Store (Marshall, Mich.) records, 1836-1927
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Brewer General Store (Marshall, Mich.) records
1836-1927
Brewer General Store (Marshall, Mich.)
85516 Bb 2
Marshall, Michigan, general store, founded by Chauncy M. Brewer and Charles T. Gorham in 1836. Daybooks, blotters, sales books, and other materials relating to the operation of the store; also records of Fink and Butler Store.
3 linear feet
25 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was the gift of Mrs. C. E. Gauss (donor no. 357 )
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Brewer General Store of Marshall was owned and operated by the same Michigan family for almost 100 years. The store was founded in June 1836 as a partnership venture of Chauncy M. Brewer and Charles T. Gorham. Although this partnership lasted but four years, the store continued to be managed by Brewer family members until 1926. Brewer General Store first did business just five years after the founding of Marshall. In a sense then, the store grew with the city, and its history is the history of Marshall itself.
Chauncy Brewer was born in 1814 in Oneonto County, New York. He lived on a family farm until 1827, when he became a clerk in a local general store. He continued working in the store until 1834 when he and a boyhood friend, Charles Gorham, struck out to the West to make their fortunes. During 1835 Brewer worked in a general store in Clinton, Michigan. In 1836 he and Gorham toured the southern part of Michigan's lower peninsula looking for a suitable location to open their own general store. In June 1836, they opened a store in Marshall. In 1840 Gorham dissolved the partnership to enter banking.
Brewer replaced Gorham with two new partners, his brothers-in-law Edward Butler and John Dusenbury. Despite these family ties, the partnership was dissolved in 1845 and Brewer chose to operate the store as its sole owner.
As time passed Brewer's sons became increasingly involved in the business, while Brewer himself increasingly was interested in other financial matters. In 1873, with the rebuilding of their building, Chauncy Brewer stepped aside and his sons, Edgar G. and Charles D., became the business' proprietors. This partnership ended in 1890 when Charles left the business and Edgar became its sole owner.
While the record is unclear, Edgar may have sold the store to H.E. Hart of Battle Creek about 1900. If the sale did occur, by 1905 the Brewer family had regained control of the business. The family continued to operate the store until 1926 when it was sold.
For most of this period the store specialized in dry goods, although it always carried a selection of other goods. At some point in the late nineteenth century the business began to carry a few groceries. After 1905 they also carried an extensive line of groceries along with the firm's more traditional merchandise. The venture into groceries, however, seems to have been unsuccessful and the store's merchandise became increasingly more narrow. By 1926 it seems to have carried dry goods exclusively.
The records of the Brewer store are very full. Most significant are the firm's daybooks, which are virtually complete for the entire period of the Brewer's operation of the store. Such gaps as exist are adequately documented through secondary record groups, such as blotters and salesbooks. In addition to this complete documentation of the goods sold each day, their price and purchaser, there are several inventories, a few timebooks, and a small body of correspondence related to the store.
The Brewer family was also involved in local real estate speculation and agricultural production, and a few records documenting these interests were retained with the store's records. Most complete is the hay scale register, covering the years 1839 to 1879. There are also records of land purchases, both in rural areas and in Marshall's "Eagle Block" which the family owned; land rental agreements; and timebooks apparently for laborers who worked the family's farmland.
Finally, the collection contains a few records generated by firms not owned by the Brewer's themselves. Most interesting are those of the Ceresco Mill, Ceresco Distillery, and the Fink & Butler store in Marshall. These records, however, are very incomplete.
The majority of the Brewer records retained at the Michigan Historical Collections are available on microfilm only. Filming was selective and information that was redundant or of minimal value was not placed on film. All original material not retained by the Michigan Historical Collections, whether filmed or not, has been placed on permanent loan with the Marshall Historical Society.
Subjects:
Brewer, Chauncy M. (Chauncy Marble), 1814-1889.; Business records.; Fink and Butler Store (Marshall, Mich.); General stores--Michigan--Marshall.; Gorham, Charles T., 1812-1901.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Marshall.; Marshall (Mich.)--History.
- Store Accounts
  - Correspondence
    - 1840 (Box 1)
    - 1841 (Box 1)
    - 1842 (Box 1)
    - Letterpress books, 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Inventories
    - April 1836 (Box 1)
    - October 1840, 2 volumes (Box 1)
    - And lists of accounts received, April 1842 (Box 1)
    - And account with city of Marshall, March 1847 (Box 1)
    - March 1851 (Box 1)
    - 1912 (Box 1)
    - January 1914 (Box 1)
  - Memoranda
    - September 1837 (Box 1)
    - October 1839 (Box 1)
  - Invoices
    - May 1836-October 1839 (Box 1)
    - January 1909 (Box 1)
  - Timebooks
    - 1893-1906 (Box 1)
    - 1906-1918 (Box 1)
  - Machine Repair Account Book, 1875-1876 (Box 1)
  - Fast Express, 1877 (Box 1)
- Farm Accounts
  - Hay Scales Register
    - 1839-1852 (Box 2)
    - January 1853-September 1855 (Box 2)
    - October 1855, July 1857 (Box 2)
    - June 1858-January 1862 (Box 2)
    - February 1862-March 1864 (Box 2)
    - March 1864-May 1865 (Box 2)
    - June 1865-July 1866 (Box 2)
    - August 1866-March 1868 (Box 2)
    - March 1868-February 1870 (Box 2)
    - February 1870-October 1874 (Box 2)
    - October 1874-June 1879 (Box 2)
  - Rents, Leases, Contracts
    - 1879-1883 (Box 2)
    - 1881-1891 (Box 2)
  - Timebooks
    - 1873-1874 (Box 2)
    - 1881-1893 (Box 2)
  - Journal
    - 1883-1915 (Box 2)
    - circa 1900 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1843-1844 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Eagle Block Property
    - Accounts
      - 1869-1882 (Box 3)
      - 1894-1906 (Box 3)
      - 1906-1916 (Box 3)
    - Donation Subscriptions, 1875-1878 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1869-1884 (Box 3)
  - Ceresco Mills Account book, May 1840-July 1842 (Box 3)
  - Ceresco Distillery
    - 1840-1842 (Box 3)
    - October 1842 (Box 3)
    - August 1842-1844 (Box 3)
  - Account of P.F. Brewer, January 1839-May 1839 (Box 3)
- Daybooks
  - June 1836-July 1837 (Box 4, Reel 1)
  - July 1837-February 1838 (Box 4, Reel 1)
  - February-November 1838 (Box 4, Reel 1)
  - November 1838-June 1839 (Box 4, Reel 1)
  - June-November 1839 (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - November 1839-June 1840 (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - June 1840-August 1846 (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - March 1841-August 1841 (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - January-June 1842 (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - (cont), January-June 1842 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - June-November 1842 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - November 1842-June 1843 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - June-December 1843 (Box 4, Reel 3)
  - (cont), June-December 1843 (Box 4, Reel 4)
  - December 1843-June 1844 (Box 4, Reel 4)
  - September 1844-February 1849 (Box 4, Reel 4)
  - March 1845-April 1846 (Box 4, Reel 4)
  - April-December 1846 (Box 4, Reel 4)
  - December 1846-September 1847 (Box 4, Reel 4)
  - (Cont), December 1846-September 1847 (Box 4, Reel 5)
  - September 1847-May 1848 (Box 4, Reel 5)
  - May 1848-January 1849 (Box 4, Reel 5)
  - January-March 1849 (Box 4, Reel 5)
  - March-September 1849 (Box 4, Reel 5)
  - February-October 1850 (Box 4, Reel 5)
  - (cont), February-October 1850 (Box 4, Reel 6)
  - October 1850-November 1851 (Box 4, Reel 6)
  - November 1851-February 1853 (Box 4, Reel 6)
  - February 1853-February 1854 (Box 4, Reel 6)
  - February 1854-February 1855 (Box 4, Reel 6)
  - (cont), February 1854-February 1855 (Box 4, Reel 7)
  - February-December 1855 (Box 4, Reel 7)
  - December 1855-November 1856 (Box 4, Reel 7)
  - November 1856-October 1857 (Box 4, Reel 7)
  - October 1857-July 1858 (Box 4, Reel 7)
  - July 1858-May 1859 (Box 4, Reel 7)
  - (Cont), July 1858-May 1859 (Box 4, Reel 8)
  - May 1859-June 1860 (Box 4, Reel 8)
  - June 1860-October 1861 (Box 4, Reel 8)
  - October 1861-December 1862 (Box 4, Reel 8)
  - December 1862-May 1864 (Box 4, Reel 8)
  - (cont), December 1862-May 1864 (Box 4, Reel 9)
  - May 1864-October 1865 (Box 4, Reel 9)
  - October 1865-March 1867 (Box 4, Reel 9)
  - March 1867-September 1868 (Box 4, Reel 9)
  - September 1868-September 1871 (Box 4, Reel 9)
  - September 1871-January 1876 (Box 4, Reel 9)
  - (cont), September 1871-January 1876 (Box 4, Reel 10)
  - April 1874-November 1875 (Box 4, Reel 10)
  - November 1875-December 1876 (Box 4, Reel 10)
  - December 1876-September 1878 (Box 4, Reel 10)
  - September 1878-December 1879 (Box 4, Reel 10)
  - (cont), September 1878-December 1879 (Box 4, Reel 11)
  - December 1879-November 1880 (Box 4, Reel 11)
  - November 1880-November 1881 (Box 4, Reel 11)
  - November 1881-October 1882 (Box 4, Reel 11)
  - October 1882-November 1883 (Box 4, Reel 11)
  - November 1883-November 1884 (Box 4, Reel 11)
  - (cont), November 1883-November 1884 (Box 4, Reel 12)
  - November 1884-December 1885 (Box 4, Reel 12)
  - December 1885-October 1887 (Box 4, Reel 12)
  - October 1867-March 1889 (Box 4, Reel 12)
  - March 1889-August 1890 (Box 4, Reel 12)
  - August 1890-October 1891 (Box 4, Reel 12)
  - (cont), August 1890-October 1891 (Box 4, Reel 13)
  - October 1891-September 1892 (Box 4, Reel 13)
  - September 1892-October 1893 (Box 4, Reel 13)
  - October 1893-December 1894 (Box 4, Reel 13)
  - December 1894-February 1896 (Box 4, Reel 13)
  - (cont), December 1894-February 1896 (Box 4, Reel 14)
  - February 1896-July 1897 (Box 4, Reel 14)
  - July 1897-April 1900 (Box 4, Reel 14)
  - July 1905-July 1906 (Box 4, Reel 14)
  - July 1906-February 1907 (Box 4, Reel 14)
  - February-July 1907 (Box 4, Reel 14)
  - (cont), February-July 1907 (Box 4, Reel 15)
  - July 1907-January 1908 (Box 4, Reel 15)
  - January-April 1908 (Box 4, Reel 15)
  - April-July 1908 (Box 4, Reel 15)
  - July-September 1908 (Box 4, Reel 15)
  - (cont), July-September 1908 (Box 4, Reel 16)
  - September-December 1908 (Box 4, Reel 16)
  - December 1908-March 1909 (Box 4, Reel 16)
  - March-May 1909 (Box 4, Reel 16)
  - May-July 1909 (Box 4, Reel 16)
  - July-September 1909 (Box 4, Reel 16)
  - September-December 1909 (Box 4, Reel 16)
  - (cont), September-December 1909 (Box 4, Reel 17)
  - December 1909-February 1910 (Box 4, Reel 17)
  - March-May 1910 (Box 4, Reel 17)
  - May-June 1910 (Box 4, Reel 17)
  - June-August 1910 (Box 4, Reel 17)
  - August-October 1910 (Box 4, Reel 17)
  - (cont), August-October 1910 (Box 4, Reel 18)
  - October-November 1910 (Box 4, Reel 18)
  - November 1910-January 1911 (Box 4, Reel 18)
  - January-March 1911 (Box 4, Reel 18)
  - March-May 1911 (Box 4, Reel 18)
  - May-July 1911 (Box 4, Reel 18)
  - (cont), May-July 1911 (Box 4, Reel 19)
  - July-August 1911 (Box 4, Reel 19)
  - August-October 1911 (Box 4, Reel 19)
  - October-December 1911 (Box 4, Reel 19)
  - December 1911-January 1912 (Box 4, Reel 19)
  - December 1911-January 1912 (Box 4, Reel 20)
  - March-May 1912 (Box 4, Reel 20)
  - May-June 1912 (Box 4, Reel 20)
  - June-August 1912 (Box 4, Reel 20)
  - August 1912-February 1914 (Box 4, Reel 20)
  - February 1914-September 1915 (Box 4, Reel 20)
  - February 1914-September 1915 (Box 4, Reel 21)
  - September 1915-November 1917 (Box 4, Reel 21)
  - November 1917-October 1919 (Box 4, Reel 21)
  - October 1919-July 1921 (Box 4, Reel 21)
  - July 1921-August 1923 (Box 4, Reel 21)
  - August 1923-September 1925 (Box 4, Reel 21)
  - October 1925-September 1927 (Box 4, Reel 21)
- Blotters, sales books, etc.
  - May-September 1841 (Box 4, Reel 21)
  - (cont), May-September 1841 (Box 4, Reel 22)
  - September 1841-January 1842 (Box 4, Reel 22)
  - December 1848-November 1849 (Box 4, Reel 22)
  - November 1849-April 1850 (Box 4, Reel 22)
  - March 1899-January 1901 (Box 4, Reel 22)
  - May 1902-July 1902 (Box 4, Reel 22)
  - September 1902-April 1903 (Box 4, Reel 22)
  - April 1903-July 1903 (Box 4, Reel 22)
  - July 1903-October 1903 (Box 4, Reel 22)
  - October 1903-December 1903 (Box 4, Reel 22)
  - December 1903-April 1904 (Box 4, Reel 22)
  - (cont), December 1903-April 1904 (Box 4, Reel 23)
  - April 1904-July 1904 (Box 4, Reel 23)
  - August 1904-November 1904 (Box 4, Reel 23)
  - November 1904-February 1905 (Box 4, Reel 23)
  - February 1905-July 1905 (Box 4, Reel 23)
  - October 1903-December 1905 (Box 4, Reel 23)
  - February 1911-February 1912 (Box 4, Reel 23)
  - February-July 1912 (Box 4, Reel 23)
  - December 1911-February 1912 (Box 4, Reel 23)
  - February-April 1912 (Box 4, Reel 23)
  - August 1911-June 1912 (Box 4, Reel 23)
  - December 1911-June 1912 (Box 4, Reel 23)
  - March 1905-February 1919 (Box 4, Reel 23)
  - (cont), March 1905-February 1919 (Box 4, Reel 24)
- Fink and Butler Store
  - Daybooks
    - May 1842-October 1842 (Box 4, Reel 24)
    - November 1842-May 1843 (Box 4, Reel 24)
    - May 1843-October 1843 (Box 4, Reel 24)
    - October 1843-March 1844 (Box 4, Reel 24)
    - June 1844-May 1845 (Box 4, Reel 24)
    - May 1845-October 1846 (Box 4, Reel 24)
  - Invoice book, May 1842-April 1847 (Box 4, Reel 24)
  - Ledger, May 1842-January 1846 (Box 4, Reel 24)
  - Ledger (cont), May 1842-January 1846 (Box 4, Reel 25)
  - Negative microfilm of daybooks and other business records (reels 1-25) (Box 5)
    [staff use only]